<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly mans gain; and the wicked mans woe; or, Good news from Heaven for the righteous Plainly shewing the wonderful manifestation of the love of God to their souls, their blessed and happy condition, both in this life and that which is to come. Likewise, the dreadful condition of the wicked, their danger by reason of sin, because of the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven against the workers of iniquity. Lastly, some seasonalble warnings, and perswasions, for poor sinners to prepare for judgement, that they may be able to stand in the evil day, and avoid those visible tokens of Gods fury, and their eternal ruine in flames of fire, prepared for the wicked, who delight to make void the law of God. By Matthew Killiray.</title>
            <author>Killiray, Matthew.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25481</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835114</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207028</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248540494</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K475</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835114</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99835114e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1970:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly mans gain; and the wicked mans woe; or, Good news from Heaven for the righteous Plainly shewing the wonderful manifestation of the love of God to their souls, their blessed and happy condition, both in this life and that which is to come. Likewise, the dreadful condition of the wicked, their danger by reason of sin, because of the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven against the workers of iniquity. Lastly, some seasonalble warnings, and perswasions, for poor sinners to prepare for judgement, that they may be able to stand in the evil day, and avoid those visible tokens of Gods fury, and their eternal ruine in flames of fire, prepared for the wicked, who delight to make void the law of God. By Matthew Killiray.</title>
                  <author>Killiray, Matthew.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for W. Thackeray, at the Black-Spread-Eagle and Sun, in the Old Bayley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">God --  Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sin, Mortal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207028:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207028:1"/>
            <p>THE Godly Mans Gain; AND THE Wicked Mans Woe; OR, Good news from Heaven for the Righteous.</p>
            <p>Plainly shewing the wonderful manifestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the love of God to their souls, their blessed and happy condition, both in this life and that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Likewise, the dreadful condition of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, their danger by reason of sin, because the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven against the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Lastly, some seasonable warnings, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions, for poor sinners to prepare for judgement, that they may be able to stand in the evil day, and avoid those visible tokens of Gods fury, and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ruine in flames of fire, prepared for the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who delight to make void the law of God.</p>
            <p>By Matthew Killiray.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Psal 9. 6, 7.</bibl>
               <p>Upon the wicked be shall rain snares, fire and brimstone, and an horrible tempest, this shall bee the portion of their Cup.</p>
               <p>For the Righteous Lord, loveth righteousness, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance doth behold the upright.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Thackeray,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Sun,</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayley.</hi> 1665.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207028:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207028:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:207028:3"/>
            <head>The Godly Mans Gain, AND The Wicked Mans Woe; OR, Good news from Heaven for the Righteous.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Isaiah 3. 10, 11.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Say yee to the Righteous, that it shall be well with them, for they shall eat the fruit of their doings.</p>
                  <p>Woe unto the wicked, it shall bee ill with him, for the reward of his hands shall bee given him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese words, are the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> unto rebellious <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> having shewed them in the former verses, the trouble and confusion which comes by sin; It is the cause of the loss of Temporal and Spiritual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thence ariseth disobedience to Parents, as you may read in the fift and sixt verses, hee comes in these two verses read to you, to shew that though it be a day of publick calamity, when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:207028:3"/> the shews of mens countenances do witnesse against them, and shews their Sin as <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet then is there good news from Heaven for the Righteous soul, here is glad tydings of peace and safety for him, <hi>It shall bée well with him;</hi> here is all good things comprehended in this word, <hi>Well,</hi> it shall go Well with him here, well with him hereafter; this shall bee his comfort, this his joy, <hi>Hée shall eat of the fruit of his Doings,</hi> and be satisfied. But what shall become of the Wicked? shall it be so with them? read the next verse, behold their doom and avoid it, if possible, <hi>Woe to the Wicked, it shall bée ill with him, for the reward of his hands shall bée given him.</hi> Better for him hee had never been born, for eternal misery is his Portion, hee hath done ill, and the fruits of his evil deeds shall hee receive; not a word of mercy to him, not a word of comfort for him; he hath had his good things in this life, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God their evil things; but now they are comforted, and he is tormented; they have the good spirit, the Holy Ghost, to comfort them, but the Wicked man, the evil spirit to torment him; in a word, all the woes and denunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of wrath shall bee executed against him, which are written in the Book of God. The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation that I would note from these words, is this.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:207028:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That in the midst of misery, the Lord Iesus Christ hath bowels of mercy for the Righteous person; but in the day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, hée will have nothing but dregs of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Wicked, who study to make void his Law.</p>
            <p>Here is good news for you, who have fought the good fight of Faith, who have contended earnestly for the cause of Christ: a Crown of glory is prepared for them which shall never fade away: There is mercy for them in the midst of misery, joy for them in the midst of sorrow; the smiles of Gods countenance shall cheer up their hearts, though they may have sorrow for a season, yet joy cometh in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; the sweet and gracious carriage of the Lord Jesus Christ shall even Ravish their souls. That this is so, <hi>that in the midst of misery, the Lord Iesus Christ hath bowels of mercy,</hi> see Heb. 13. 5. <hi>Bée content with such things as you have, for hée hath said, I will never leave thée, nor forsake thée;</hi> As if the Lord should say to any poor soul in misery, that is ready to dispond or despair, under the burden of his afflictions, bear my hand patiently, bee content with such as you have, whether it be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, tribulation, or persecution in this world; I have prepared a better Kingdome for you, Ile never leave you, in six troubles, or in seven, <hi>Ile
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207028:4"/> guide you by my Counsel, and afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you into Glory.</hi> Psa. 138. 3. <hi>In the day when I cryed, thou answeredst mée, and strengthenedst mée with strength in my Soul.</hi> Though the world frown upon them, yet there is a secret support, there is an everlasting arm that bears them up; his sweet and gracious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the Church, declares that they are the beloved of his Soul, they are his Darling, see Canticles 4. 8, 11. <hi>Come with mée from</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon <hi>(my Spouse) from</hi> Lebanon, &amp;c. <hi>thou hast Ravished my heart, my Sister, my Spouse, thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, with one Chain of thy neck, how fair is thy love, my Sister, my Spouse, how much better is thy Love than wine, and the smell of thine ointments, than all spices?</hi> and thus the Lord Jesus goes along, shewing forth his Love in most excellent tearms, to make the soul more enamored of him: But now to shew you why it is so, or how it comes to pass, that the Lord is so full of bowels of mercy towards the Righteous, I shall give a few Reasons for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because they are those whom hee hath Ransomed, whom hee hath bought at a dear rate, even the price of his own blood. These are the persons, (the Righteous I mean) for whom hee was reviled, despised, was in bitter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207028:5"/> Agonies, and suffered a cruel death upon the Crosse; And think you will he leave these in misery, and not remember, hee is a God of mercy? will not hee stay these with Flaggons, and comfort them with Apples, when they are sick of love? The blood of the Lord Jesus Christ was not shed in vain, but he dyed that his might live, hee went thorow sorrows, that his might have joy, hee was Crowned with Thorns, that his might bee Crowned with Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. They are those whom hee hath called out of darknesse into his marvellous light, for these he hath procured a salvation, and an everlasting Rest, They shall not be lead Captive at the Devils will, because they are redeemed by the blood of the Lamb. Therefore shall it go well with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because they are those whom hee hath Chosen, and those whom the Fathers hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him; Therefore hath the Lord bowels of mercy for them. As hee hath accomplished his part on the Crosse for them, so will hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish his part in Heaven for them. John 6. 36. <hi>Of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at the Father hath given him he will lose nothing.</hi> They are the fruits of his death and Resurrection, to these hee will bee a Father in time of trouble, when the world casts them off, he will receive them into his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, hee will open his everlasting arms, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207028:5"/> receive them into his embraces, Christ will not lose his interest, hee will not lose those whom hee hath chosen, and whom the Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, but the light of his countenance shall shine upon them, and hee will compasse them about with mercy all the daies of their lives.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Why hath God bowels of mercy for the Righteous? because God hath peculiarly promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to these, and none but these, that he will be a Father to them, and they shall be his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, hath not a Father yerning bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of affection towards his childe, doth not he love his own, and cherish his own more affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately then he doth anothers, if he see them wronged doth not hee right them, even so the Lord Jesus Christ, as a Father is very pityful, and very loving, and affectionate toward his Children, Oh how his spirit is grieved to see his grieved, when his children are molested, and despised, it pierceth into his soul, and presently he is ready to deliver them, he will never leave his comfortlesse, but he will come unto them, hee will bee with them in joy and sorrow, in prosperity and adversity, in life and death, and at last will lead them into his heavenly habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may partake of the glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, and receive the reward of their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, even the salvation of their precious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207028:6"/> souls. Thus have you heard why the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ hath yerning bowels of mercy towards the Righteous. Indeed many more might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but these I think are enough to satisfie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reasonable soul, and now let mee proceed to make a little improvement of it by way of use.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Use of Exhortation: Let it bee to exhort you who are Righteous in the sight of God, you to whom Jesus Christ hath bowels of mercy, to be continually lifting up prayers and praises with your whole heart and soul unto the Lord, who hath translated you out of darknesse into his marvailous light, and out of the Kingdome of Satan unto God, that hee should take pity of you when you were in your blood, when the Priest, and the Levite past by, that Christ the good Samaritain should look on you, and heal you. Oh admire this goodnesse of God! and been not slothful, but be fervent in spirit, serving the Lord, that hath had such compassion on you, that hath washed your souls in his own blood, that hath purged your consciences from dead works, what, will not you serve the Lord with fear and trembling? you to whom the Lord hath revealed himself in Love and Mercy, oh be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted in the fear of God, to live answerable to those injoyments you enjoy, and are like to bee partakers of.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:207028:6"/>2. Use of comfort and consolation to poor dejected souls, who go mourning all the day long, here is good news for you converted sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, you who have felt the misery under the burden of sin, and do believe and endeavour to avoid the power of Satan, and the wrath of God, and do believe what Christ hath done for your restauration and salvation, and have thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accepted of him as your onely Saviour and Lord, on the terms that hee is offered in the Gospel, as one that calls, justifies, sanctifies, and brings at last to everlasting glory. Hold up your heads poore souls, and open the everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gates of your souls, that the King of glory may come in in tryumph; Hitherto you have clouded the bright rayes of his glory, now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your eyes and your souls, that you may behold it, learn to say with <hi>David,</hi> Why art thou cast down O my soul, why art thou dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within mee? hope thou in God, who will yet bee the light of my countenance and my God: hold up your heads, you have cause to rejoyce, O ye Saints and Servants of the most high God, you need not fear what man can do unto you, it shall bee well with you, you shall have joy when others shall have sorrow, you shall have peace when others shall have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, you shall enjoy eternal life, when others shall have eternal death to their portion, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207028:7"/> so let mee leave you in the bosome of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sucking from the breasts of his consolation, and let mee speak a little to the wicked, to those who will not have the Lord of life to Reign over them. Something I shall speak, to show them their danger and desperate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and something by way of perswasion, to perswade them to come in to the Lord Jesus Christ, that they might not bee the objects of his fury at the great day. And when I begin to speak of these things, I confesse it seems ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to mee, and makes mee almost afraid; people will run out of their wits when they hear it, but a little experience shewing us that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are like a Dog bread up in a Forge or Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, that being used to it, can sleep though the hammers are beating, and the fire and hot Irons flaming about him, when another that had never seen it would be amazed at the sight: so thus they who have ten or twenty years heard talke of the danger of enduring the wrath of God at the day of judgement, but see it not, nor feel any hurt, they think it is but talke, and make nothing of it, and thus they thank God for his patience, <hi>Because his sentence is not executed spéedily therefore they set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to do evil. Eccles.</hi> 8. 11. This consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration moved mee, and awakened my soul, that I might unburden my conscience before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207028:7"/> you, and speak the truth in God and lye not. And Oh that I could reach your hearts, Oh that whosoever reads this little book, might fear and tremble, and that seeing his danger he may endeavour to avoid those unquenchable flames of the fury of Gods wrath, see 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10, 11. and tremble when you read it, <hi>For wée must all appear at the Iudgement seat of Christ, that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, good or bad. Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing therefore the terrours of the Lord we perswade men.</hi> 'Tis to you I am to speak who have done ill, woe to you, for the reward of your works shall bee given you, and what is that? Nothing but hell and horrour, nothing but the fury of Gods wrath; a sad sentence shall bee passed on you, shall make your hearts to tremble then, though you will not tremble now.</p>
            <p>1. Let us inquire wherein this horrour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists, that is, first in the sentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it self, which expresseth the misery they are judged to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are cursed, and that denounceth a people destinated and adjudged to utter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happinesse, and to all kinde of miseries without remedy; and their cursednesse is described in the next words; <hi>depart from mée into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting fire, prepared for the Devil and his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207028:8"/> Angels;</hi> from whom must they depart? from that God that made them in his Image, from the Redeemer that Bought them with the price of his blood, and offered to save them freely, for all their unworthiness, and many times intreated them to accept his offer, that their souls might live; from the Holy Ghost, the sanctifier, and comforter of the Faithful, who strove with their hearts, till they quenched and expelled him: Oh sad departing! who would not then chuse to depart from all the friends hee had in the world, or from any thing imaginable, from his life, from himself, if it were possible, than from Christ; <hi>Depart,</hi> from what? from the presence of the Judge, from all future hopes of salvation for ever, from all possibility of ever being saved, and living in the joyful inheritance of the Righteous. And then consider</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether must they depart? 1. Into fire. 2. Into that fire, which is prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels. 3. Into everlasting fire, not into a purifying, but into a tormenting fire, and thither wilt thou go without remedy, no Christ now to intercede for thee; in vain now to repent, and wish you had not slighted your salvation, or sold it for a little pleasure for the flesh, it will bee then in vain to cry, <hi>Lord open to us;</hi> Oh spare us! Oh pity us! Oh do not cast us into those hideous flames! Oh do not turn us among
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207028:8"/> Devils, do not condemn thy Redeemed ones! but all shall bee in vain, you cry and you call too late, the gates of Heaven are shut against you, you have sinned, therefore you shall suffer; the coals of his fury shall alwaies bee burning of you, but you shall never be burnt; considering the company you shall have, none but torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Devils, this will aggravate your misery; and the time it shall endure, not only a year, or ten years, or a hundred years, but for ever; you shall bee alwaies consuming, but never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed; as the blessedness and joy of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is perpetual, so shall also the torments of the Wicked. Oh poor sinner! that readest or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est these lines, I beseech thee, in compassion to thy soul, consider how fearful the case of that man will bee, that is newly doomed to the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting fire, and is haled to the execution with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy. The time was, when Repentance might have done thee good, but then all thy Repentings will bee in vain; now while thy day of visitation lasteth, hadst thou but a heart to cry and call for mercy in faith and fervency, thou mightest bee heard, but then praying and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will do thee no good; shouldst thou roar out in the extremity of thy horrour and amazement, and beseech the Lord Jesus, but to forgive thee one sin, or to send thee on earth once more, or try thee once again in the flesh, whether
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207028:9"/> thou would love him, and lead a holy life, it would bee all in vain; shouldst thou beseech him by all the mercifulness of his nature, by all his sufferings and bloody death, by all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful promises of the Gospel, it would bee all in vain; nay shouldst thou but beg for one daies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve, or to stay one hour before thou wert cast into those flames, it would not bee heard; how earnestly did <hi>Dives</hi> hog of <hi>Abraham,</hi> for one drop of water to cool his tongue, because hee was tormented in the flames, and what was hee the better, hee was bid <hi>Remember the good things hée had in this life,</hi> and that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance would torment him more. Christ will not bee intreated by the ungodly, but hee will soon stop thy mouth, or leave thee speechless and say, Remember man that I did once send thee a message of peace, and thou wouldst not hear it, I did once stoop to beseech thee to return, and thou wouldst not hear, I besought thee by the tender mercies of God; I besought thee by all the love that I had shewed thee, by my holy life, my cursed death, by the riches of my grace, by the offers of my glory, and I could not get thee to forsake the world, to deny thy flesh, to leave one beloved sin; for all this, I waited on thee many a day, and year, thou wouldst not consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and return and live, and now 'tis too late, my sentence is past, and cannot be recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207028:9"/> away from me, get thee hence, <hi>thou work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Iniquity,</hi> Mat. 7. 22, 23. Ah! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved friends, what a case is then the poor des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate sinner left in? how can you that read or hear, once think without trembling, of the condition that such forlorn wretches will be in, when they look above them, and see God that hath forsaken them, because they forsook him first; and when they look about them, and see the Saints on the one hand, whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised, now sentenced unto glory, and the Wicked on the other hand, whom they accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied and imitated, now judged with them to everlasting misery; when they look below them, and see the flames that they must abide in, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for evermore, and when the Devil begins to hale them to the execution; Oh poor souls! now what would they give for a Christ, for a promise, for a time of Repentance, for a Sermon of mercy, which once they slept under, or made no account of; how is the case altered now with them? who would think that these are the same men, that made light of all this on earth, that so stoutly scorned the reproofs of the word, that would be worldly, and fleshly, &amp; drunk, &amp; proud; let preachers say what they would, and perhaps hated them that did give them warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; now they are of another minde, but all too late; now would they draw back, and lay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207028:10"/> hold of any thing, rather than bee dragged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into those flames, but there is no resisting; Satans temptations might have been resisted, but his executions cannot; Gods Judgements might have been prevented by faith and prayer, and a holy life, but they cannot bee resisted, when they are not prevented; glad would the miserable sinner bee, if that hee might but turn to nothing, or that hee might bee any thing, rather than a Reasonable Creature, but their wishes are all in vain, there is but one time, and one way for a sinners deliverance, if hee fail in that one, hee perisheth for ever; all the world cannot help him after that, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 26. I have heard thee in a time accepted, and in a day of salvation, behold now is the day of salvation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>Behold I stand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voyce, and open the door, I will come in to him, and sup with him, and hée with mée,</hi> but for the time to come hereafter, hear what the Lord saith, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1, 24, 25, 26. <hi>because I have called and you refused, I have stretched out my hand and no man regarded, but they have set at naught all my counsel, and would none of my reproof I will also mock at your calamity,</hi> I <hi>will laugh when your fear cometh; when your fear cometh as desolation, and your destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a whirl-wind, when distress and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207028:10"/> cometh upon them; then shall they call upon mée, but I will not answer, they shall séek mée early, but shall not finde mée, for that they hated knowledge, and did not chuse the fear of the Lord. They would none of my counsels, they despised all my reproofs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shall they eat of the fruit of their owne way, and bée filled with their own devices, for the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them, but who so hearkneth to me, shall dwell safely, and shall bee quiet from fear of evil.</hi> This God himself hath plainly told you, and Oh! that you would consider of it in time; will you thus wilfully sin, and think to escape the wrath of God? nay, let me tell you, <hi>except you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise repent, yée shall all likewise perish;</hi> all the world shall not, cannot save you, no Act of Indemnity shall be passed upon you, you have sinned, and you shall suffer, and Gods name shall be justified by it, and Ah! that your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences would be awakned by a serious appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of the deadly torments, and smoaking flames that shall certainly one day ceize upon your body, and that the fear of it might move your hearts into a relenting and repenting frame, and your souls might bee affected with the ways and truths of God, which are both pleasant and peaceable, and in them you shall finde et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nal life.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:207028:11"/>
            <p>And now I have in brief shewn you the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of resisting the Lord Jesus Christ, suffer mee to perswade you, and Oh that you would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, before the woes and denunciations of Gods wrath be pronounced against you! Oh that you would beleeve that one day you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the fruit of your doings, will you suffer your souls to sink in the last day, for want of care and self-preservation? Oh that I could perswade you by the tender mercies of God, by that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of the immaculate Lamb of God, to awake presently, and resolve to lose no more time, but set upon the work. Oh that there were such a heart in you, as you were truly willing to follow the gracious guidance of the Lord, and to use those sweet and reasonable means which he hath used in his Word, that you may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the day of the Lord, for you will not bee able to make any shift to keep your souls from continual terrours, as long as you remain in a carnal and unregenerate condition; let the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den approach of death and judgement continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally move you, and the terrible apprehensions of the falling into those furious flames prepared for the wicked, rouse up your sleepy souls from sin and security. How do you think to escape at the last day, you that never once trembled at the thoughts of that great day. Let mee perswade you to confirme your thoughts in the belief of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207028:11"/> this, that you shall suddenly appear at the Bar of Gods justice, and there shalt be brought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for thy deeds done in the flesh, whether good or evil, what then wilt thou be able to say before the great God, then it will be too late to say, <hi>Lord be merciful to mée a sinner,</hi> then shal you wish too late, that you had done the good, and the acceptable will of God? and that you had left the Creature, and served the Creator. Then shall you be ready to cry out, wo is mee, how shall I be able to bear this heavy and dreadful burden of the wrath of God? Oh how shall I live among those scorching and never dying flames? How shall I be able to endure those fearful shriecks, and sad complaints of those damned souls? and then beholding the sweet harmony that is among the glorified Saints, their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual blessednesse shall more amaze thee, then wilt thou wish thou weart received into their sweet society; Then wilt thou be ready to say, <hi>Lord receive mée into thy Kingdom.</hi> But alas thou hadst thy good things in this life, therefore nothing but wrath and curse is thy portion, this will be thy condition, unlesse thou in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, and carefully prepare for the comming of the Bride, I would lay down a few helps and directions, to poor seduced and deluded souls, that seeing their danger, they might also look out for a Recovery.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:207028:12"/>
            <p>The first <hi>Direction,</hi> Labour to get your souls established in this belief, that the judgement of the great day is at hand, and that you must answer for all your deeds done in the flesh; friends, shut not your eyes against the light. If you do not believe such a day is at hand, you will never prepare for it, it is the word of the God of truth, certainly you dare not give him the lye. <hi>John</hi> 5. 28, 29. <hi>The hour is coming in which all that are in their graves shall hear his voyce, and shall come forth, they that have done good to the Resurrection of life, and they that have done evil to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of damnation.</hi> Heb. 9. 27. <hi>It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to all men once to dye, and after death to Iudgement.</hi> Nothing more true then this, and dare you live without the faith of this.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Direction.</hi> Make it the business of your lives to be ready for that day. All other business should depend upon this, what else have you to do but to provide for eternity, and to use the means prescribed in Gods Word? remember when you awake every morning you are nearer to eternity, and that the day of your account is at hand, and when you go to bed, examine your hearts, what you have done in preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the last day, are you ready for judgement, or are you not? Consider a while with your souls, doth not the Scriptures say, <hi>Except a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207028:12"/> man bée born again, hée cannot enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> Joh. 3. 3. <hi>And this is the condemnation that Light is come into the World, and men love Darkness rather than Light, because their déeds are evil.</hi> See the case of the unprepared soul, at the great day Mat. 25. <hi>Cast the unprofitable servant into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, there shall bée wéeping and gnashing of téeth. But those mine enemies who will not have me to reign over them, bring them hither and slay them before mée.</hi> Mat. 22. 12, 13. <hi>Friend, how camest thou hither not having a wedding garment? and hée was spéechlesse, then said the King to the servants, binde him hand and foot, and take him away, cast him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to utter darknesse.</hi> Labour to bee ready for the great day.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Direction.</hi> Get faith and repentance sown in thy heart, or else thou shalt never bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or justified by the blood of Christ. Without faith it is impossible to please God, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance no salvation. Oh make not a light matter of sin and misery, least thou bee pressed by them into infernal flames, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent from the bottome of thy heart, and bee grieved for this, that thou didst not repent soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Turn to the Lord with thy whole heart, and let God bee in all your thoughts, then hee will pardon and pass by all your iniquities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207028:13"/> you graciously, and present you as pure and spotless before the throne of his Father, and then you shall bee taken into his embraces, and have his banner of love spread over you.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Direction.</hi> Let it bee the daily care of your souls to mortifie fleshly desires, and overcome the world, fleshly desires and carnal self will draw you off from God. This therefore must bee the earnest work of thy life, to subdue this flesh, and to set light by this world, and resist the devil that would destroy thee; live loose from all things in this world, if you would bee ready for another world, you must not live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the flesh, but mortifie it by the spirit; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. If you would be accepted in the last day, and bee able to give up your account with joy, this must bee the course of your life; then hee hath promised to receive you graciously, and to take you into his everlasting rest.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Direction.</hi> As you renew your Life, so day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renew your Repentance, and do all your works, as men that must bee Judged for them at the last day; Oh that you would remember when temptations are upon you! how careful you should bee of your words and thoughts; if you seriously remember you must bee judged for what you have done, and give an account for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very talent received, certainly you would not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vain, so carnal, and so dead to the things of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207028:13"/> God; were you fully convinced that you must answer for all, were God in all your thoughts, the Devil would bee under foot; Oh that poor miserable souls! would before it bee too late, lay to heart these things, and remember what they are born for, and what will bee the issue of an ungodly, careless, unrepenting life.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Direction.</hi> Bee in this vigilent and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent course, that with confidence you may rest upon God as a Father, and upon the promise of acceptance, and remission, through the merits and intercession of Jesus Christ; look up in hope to the glory that is set before you; serve not droopingly, but with love and joy, and filial fear; get into communion with the Saints, take heed you bee not excluded by your unworthy walking, lest you bee cast out of the presence of Christ and his Saints for ever. And that I might draw to a conclusion, I would say to poor sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Judgement is near, bee prepared lest thou bewail when it is too late. Oh! that the Lord would open your eyes, and turn you to himself; and then the judgement day will not bee dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to you; then your Saviour whom you have obeyed, will not condemn you, but if you will be obstinate, when the Lord Jesus Christ is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven with his mighty Angels in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, taking vengeance on them who know not God, and obey not the Gospel of our Lord
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207028:14"/> Jesus Christ, you who have resisted his will, shall bee punished with everlasting destruction, from the presence of the Lord, when the day of the Marriage of the Lamb comes, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Saints into glory, then you who are not prepared for the Bridegroome, the door shall bee shut against you, and though you cry <hi>Lord, Lord open to us,</hi> you shall bee repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a <hi>verily I know you not;</hi> when others long, hope, and wait for comfort, then shall you fear and tremble at the remembrance of it. And Oh! that the words contained in this little Book, might move some poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls to a serious view of their lives and conversations, whether they are those to whom the Lord will say, <hi>Woe to you wicked, you shall receive the fruit of your doings:</hi> that you may in time prepare for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that when the time of your departure is at hand, you may bee able to look back on the good fight you have sought, and the cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you have finished, and the faith you have kept, and may confidently conclude, that henceforth there is laid up a crown for you, of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which the Lord Jesus Christ the Judge, shall give you at the last day, and not to you only, but to all them; who love his appearing, that you may bee able to say, even so <hi>come Lord Iesus, come quickly.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:207028:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>